# Katharina Duecker

I am passionate about uncovering how the temporal dynamics of the visual system support the efficient allocation of computational resources; allowing a continuous percept of the visual world. My research involves empirical studies, using non-invasive brain recordings as well as computational modeling and computer vision.

# **EDUCATION**

2019 - 2023

**PhD in Neuroscience**, Centre For Human Brain Health, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, UK Supervisor: Prof Ole Jensen, Prof Kimron Shapiro

2016 - 2019

**MSc Neurocognitive Psychology**, Department of Psychology, Carl-von-Ossietzky University of Oldenburg, Germany Thesis: *Entrainment of Neuronal Gamma Oscillations using Rapid Frequency Tagging*Supervisor: Prof Christoph Herrmann, Grade: 1.2, Thesis: 1.0

2013 - 2016

**BSc Psychology**, Faculty of Psychology, Bielefeld University, Germany Thesis: *Attentional Capture by a Novel Stimulus in Visual Search* Supervisor: Prof Gernot Horstmann, Grade: 1.9, Thesis: 1.0

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### **DOCTORAL RESEARCH**

### Biologically plausible neuronal dynamics in Computer Vision (see abstract 7)

This project is motivated by the idea that neuronal population dynamics prevent sensory systems from getting overwhelmed by the abundance of stimuli competing for our attention. My work shows that implementing biologically plausible temporal dynamics in a neural network solves the competition between simultaneous inputs for sensory resources, and allows the system to process them in rapid succession.

### Investigating the neuronal substrates of Visual Search (poster)

Visual search is a classic experiment used to operationalize selective attention to visual objects. This project aims to uncover the neural substrates of numerous behavioral findings and their corresponding models. I use Magnetoencephalography and rapid photic stimulation to investigate how neuronal excitability in early visual cortex is modulated to solve the search task.

### Synchronizing endogenous neuronal oscillations using photic stimulation [1]

Rhythmic responses to photic stimulation are often assumed to reflect a synchronization of ongoing neuronal oscillations to the stimulus. My research challenges this view, showing that the intrinsic dynamics of the brain are not easily perturbed. This study motivates further work to understand how rhythmic sensory stimulation affects cellular activity.

### **INTERNSHIPS & STUDENT PROJECTS**

Nov 2017 – Apr 2018

 $\textbf{Electric field modeling of transcranial brain stimulation [4]}, Prof \, Christoph \, Herrmann, \, Dr \, Florian \, Kasten \, Christoph \, Christoph \, Herrmann, \, Dr \, Florian \, Christoph \,$ 

Carl-von-Ossietzky University of Oldenburg, Department of Psychology, Germany

Aug 2017 - Nov 2017

**Decision-making in pathological gambing using fMRI** [2], Dr Alexander Genauck, Prof Nina Romanczuk-Seiferth Charité Berlin, Department of Psychiatry & Psychotherapy, Germany

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Grading: 1.0 - 1.7: very good, 1.7 - 2.7: good, 2.7 - 3.7: pass, >4: fail

# **SKILLS**

Programming Other

MATLAB Psychtoolbox, fieldtrip Languages German, English, Spanish, French

Python NumPy, SciPy, MNE, PyTorch, Keras Other Digital Signal Processing, Dynamic Systems

Matplotlib, jupyter notebook, spyder Theory, Computational Neuroscience,

**R** ggplot, lme4, ez Eyetracking

other shell (bash) & ETEX

# **SUMMER SCHOOLS, MACHINE LEARNING & MATHEMATICS**

Jul 2022

Computational Neuroscience: Vision, Summer School at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Long Island, NY, USA

Jun 2022

Kavli Summer Institue in Cognitive Neuroscience, Summer School at UC Santa Barbara, California, USA

Jul 2021

**Neuromatch Academy: Deep Learning** 

Jul 2020

**Neuromatch Academy: Computational Neuroscience** 

Aug 2019

Linear Algebra for Neuroscientists, Summer School at Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands

2018/019

Machine Learning I: Unsupervised Learning, M.Sc. Physics course at the University of Oldenburg, Germany

Mar 2017

Tools for Teaching Quantitative Thinking, Erasmus+ Seminar at the University of Graz

# **GRANTS & AWARDS**

Jun 2022

Travel Grant, Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds

3,150 EUR/ 3,307.5 USD

May 2022

Howard Hughs Medical Award, CSHL course waiver

1,500 USD

Mar 2022

PhD paper of the year 2022(2nd place), Centre for Human Brain Health

Oct 2021

**Leading Women in Neuro-AI abstract award**, Montreal AI & Neuroscience meeting

400 CAD/ 324 USD

# **PUBLICATIONS**

- [1] K. Duecker, T. P. Gutteling, C. S. Herrmann, and O. Jensen, "No evidence for entrainment: Endogenous gamma oscillations and rhythmic flicker responses coexist in visual cortex," *Journal of Neuroscience*, 2021. DOI: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3134-20.2021.
- [2] A. Genauck, C. Matthis, M. Andrejevic, et al., "Neural correlates of cue-induced changes in decision-making distinguish subjects with gambling disorder from healthy controls," Addiction Biology, 2021. DOI: 10.1111/adb.12951.
- [3] A. Zhigalov, K. Duecker, and O. Jensen, "The visual cortex produces gamma band echo in response to broadband visual flicker," *PLoS Computational Biology*, 2021. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1009046.
- [4] F. H. Kasten, K. Duecker, M. C. Maack, A. Meiser, and C. S. Herrmann, "Integrating electric field modeling and neuroimaging to explain inter-individual variability of tacs effects," *Nature Communications*, 2019. DOI: 10.1038/s41467-019-13417-6.

# **CONFERENCE ABSTRACTS/TALKS**

- [5] K. Duecker, K. L. Shapiro, S. Hanslmayr, J. Wolfe, Y. Pan, and O. Jensen, "Guided search is associated with modulated neuronal excitability to target and distractor features in early visual regions," International Conference of Cognitive Neuroscience (Poster), May 2022.
- [6] K. Duecker, "Early career researcher talk: How does the visual system implement selective attention?" Psyched@UoB (Invited talk), Jun. 2021.
- [7] K. Duecker, "Oscillatory responses to sinusoidal and broadband frequency tagging: No entrainment, but a perceptual echo in the gamma-band," Neuoxillations: Early career researcher talk series by the Experimental Psychology group, University of Oxford (invited talk), Sep. 2021.
- [8] K. Duecker, M. Idiart, and O. Jensen, "Space-to-time-conversion: Oscillations in an artificial neural network generate a temporal code representing simultaneous visual inputs," Montreal AI & Neuroscience (Graphical Abstract), Nov. 2021.
- [9] K. Duecker, T. P. Gutteling, C. S. Herrmann, and O. Jensen, "No evidence for entrainment: Endogenous gamma oscillations and rhythmic flicker responses coexist in visual cortex," Neuromatch Conference 3 (Virtual poster), Nov. 2020.
- [10] K. Duecker, T. P. Gutteling, C. S. Herrmann, and O. Jensen, "Does rapid frequency tagging entrain neuronal gamma oscillations?" British Association for Cognitive Neuroscience (Poster), Sep. 2019.

# TEACHING/MENTORING

#### MENTORING

2022

Jiahui An, M.Sc. Cognitive Neuroscience and Robotics: Brain-Computer Interface based on photic stimulation

### TEACHING (M.Sc. LEVEL, SELECTED)

Autumn 2021, 2022

MEG practical, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham

 $8\ hours\ lecture+flexible\ tutoring,\ 3\ students;\ developed\ and\ taught\ an\ introductory\ course\ on\ MEG\ with\ applications\ in\ MATLAB$ 

Spring 2020, 2021, 2022

**Application of Electrophysiological Approaches**, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham 20 hours teaching/tutoring per term, grading of assignments, 40 students

Spring 2020, 2021

**MATLAB programming**, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham 10 hours teaching/tutoring per term, 40 students

Winter 2018/2019

**Fundamental competencies in Psychology**, Department of Computer Science, University of Oldenburg 20 hours teaching, weekly seminar on fundamental literature in cognitive psychology, prepared and taught teaching material, 10 students

Winter 2017/2018

**Multivariate Statistics**, Department of Psychology, University of Oldenburg 20 hours teaching, weekly tutorial on multivariate statistics, prepared repetition of weekly lectures and applications in R, 35 students

# AD HOC PEER-REVIEWING

Journal of Neuroscience; Psychophysiology; European Journal of Neuroscience; Cerebral Cortex; PLOS One; Brain & Behavior; Attention, Perception, & Psychophysics